# MARCO ROMANELLI

mobile: +33 06 15 57 95 11 email: marcoromane@gmail.com

PhD code repository: https://github.com/marcoromanelli-github

PhD graduate with three years of experience in research and programming offering a strong foundation in Computer Science with a concentration in Machine Learning and Information Theory as applied to Security and Privacy. Experienced in object-oriented programming: developing, testing and debugging code.

#### **EDUCATION**

# PhD in Computer Science

October 2020

Supervised by Catuscia Palamidessi, COMETE Team, Inria-Saclay, Paris, France University of Paris-Saclay and École Polytechnique, Paris, France Joint PhD with Università di Siena, Siena, Italy (awarded the Vinci 2018 grant).

#### M.S. in Computer Engineering

April 2017

Computer and Automation Engineering
Department of Information Engineering and Mathematics, Università di Siena, Siena, Italy
110/110 (cum laude).

#### B.S. in Computer Engineering

April 2014

Computer and Automation Engineering Department of Information Engineering and Mathematics, Università di Siena, Siena, Italy 110/110 (cum laude).

#### **EXPERIENCE**

# PhD Candidate, Inria-Saclay at École Polytechnique

October 2017 - October 2020

- · Review methods to provide privacy via noise injection, mainly Differential Privacy and its derivations.
- · Conduct research studies on how Machine Learning can improve Privacy meeting Utility and Quality of Service requirements.
- · Investigate the manner in which Machine Learning can provide Black Box noise functions that can scale to big data, and only add noise where needed.
- · Adopt privacy/utility loss functions from the field of Information Theory to design privacy oriented loss functions for Artificial Neural Networks (ANN), including applications of Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs) paradigm.
- · Design, develop and maintain code repository to support result reproducibility.
- · Presented at MILA and UQAM in Montreal (CA) as visitor student, August-September 2019.

# Intern, COMETE at Inria-Saclay

June 2017 - October 2017

- · Contributed new research topics which combine notions from the fields of Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning with those of Privacy and Security such like the connection between Information Leakage and Feature Selection.
- · Analyzed techniques for Feature Selection in classification problems with a focus on Statistical Filter Methods for their intrinsic link to Information Theory, specifically Mutual Information and Information Entropy.
- · Investigated the usage of Entropy, specifically Shannon Entropy and Rényi min-entropy, as metrics for selecting features, with a focus on how they influence the structures of the resulting Decision Trees.
- · Designed and structured an experimental pipeline to compare different selection metrics utilizing Python as programming language, the scikit-learn python library (Data analysis and Support Vector Machines), the TensorFlow and Keras libraries (Artificial Neural Networks).
- · Presented on statistics oriented techniques for Feature Selection specifically Lasso and InfoGain.

#### Data Scientist, GlaxoSmithKline plc.

September 2016 - April 2017

- · Worked with Exploratory Data Analysis Team as graduate intern student.
- Contributed expertise on the engineering and design of databases, and created an internal SQL database for storing protein experiment data.

- · Developed R code to manage connections and queries to the internal database wrapping SQL CRUD operations.
- · Contributed statistical analysis and code deployment for the STRAIN package and its corresponding publication.
- · Continue to collaborate on existing projects focused on the usage of Machine Learning techniques, in particular Support Vector Machines (SVM), for Reverse Vaccinology (ML4RV) and new antigens prediction.

#### Java Developer, RedEvo Games

April 2014 - September 2014

- · Contributed to the development of an online strategic card game.
- · Deployed code for front-end/back-end application to manage card creation and deletion, and update on a remote server.
- · Debugged existing code to correct errors.
- · Assisted with front-end client graphic interface using java.awt and java.swing.
- · Helped develop back-end server side application handling of front-end/back-end communications via Java Web Services.

# **TEACHING**

CSE103 - Introduction to Algorithms, École Polytechnique, Academic Year 2017-2018.

INF442 - Algorithms for Big Data Analysis, École Polytechnique, Academic Year 2017-2018.

CSE101 - Computer Programming, École Polytechnique, Academic Year 2018-2019.

# PROGRAMMING SKILLS

Programming Languages: C, C++, Python, Java, R, Bash, SQL, CUDA, Arduino, HTML, PHP.

Frameworks and Libraries: TensorFlow, SciKit, Caret.

Deployment: Git, SVN, Jupiter Notebooks.

Client-Server Technology: RESTful Web Services (RWS), Apache Tomcat.

Document Preparation Systems: LATEX, Markdown.

Operative Systems: MacOS, Linux (Ubuntu Desktop, Ubuntu Server Edition, Arch Linux), CentOS, Windows.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

#### Estimating g-Leakage via Machine Learning.

[Git repository] [Paper]

Marco Romanelli, Konstantinos Chatzikokolakis, Catuscia Palamidessi and Pablo Piantanida

Proceedings of the 27th ACM SIGSAC Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS 2020).

#### Modern Applications of Game-Theoretic Principles (Invited Paper).

[Paper]

Catuscia Palamidessi, Marco Romanelli

Proceedings of the 31st LIPICS International Conference on Concurrency Theory, (CONCUR 2020).

### Optimal Obfuscation Mechanisms via Machine Learning.

[Git repository] [Paper]

Marco Romanelli, Catuscia Palamidessi and Konstantinos Chatzikokolakis

Proceedings of the 33rd IEEE Computer Security Foundations Symposium (CSF 2020).

# Generating Optimal Privacy-Protection Mechanisms via Machine Learning (Extended abstract).

Marco Romanelli, Catuscia Palamidessi and Konstantinos Chatzikokolakis

Privacy Preserving Machine Learning Workshop (PPML) co-located with 26th ACM SIGSAC Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS 2019).

# Feature selection in machine learning: Rényi min-entropy vs Shannon entropy. [Git repository] [Paper]

Catuscia Palamidessi and Marco Romanelli

Proceedings of the 8th International Association for Pattern Recognition TC3 Workshop on Artificial Neural Networks in Pattern Recognition, (ANNPR 2018).

STRAIN: an R package for multi-locus sequence typing from whole genome sequencing data. [Paper]

Mattia Dalsass, Margherita Bodini, Christophe Lambert, Marie-Cecile Mortier, Marco Romanelli, Duccio Medini, Alessandro Muzzi and Alessandro Brozzi  $BMC\ Bioinformatics.$